Turn to the right,
milady.
Thank you.
That's it.
Hear ye,
hear ye, hear ye!
Lords! Knights! Squires!
And all other
manner of people.
That by the command of Our
Lord, the king of France,
it is strictly prohibited,
on pain of death
and the loss of property,
for anyone here
to be armed,
or to carry
a sword or dagger
unless he be one who has
the express permission
of Our Lord, the king.
Each man is to fight
on horseback and on foot,
armed in the manner
that pleases him,
with any weapon or device
of attack or defense.
Except for weapons or
devices of equal design
or made with
charms or spells
or any other thing that is
forbidden by God and holy church
to all good Christians.
If either combatant should
carry onto the field of battle
any arms that have been
forged with spells,
charms, enchantments,
or any other evil arts,
then so shall the malefactor
be punished as an enemy of God
or as a traitor
or as a murderer.
- Tighter. Tighter.
- Monsieur.
Knights, proceed.
Let them go!
Let them go! Let them go!
Come for your fight!
You're all gonna die!
You're all gonna die
like pigs!
Come on, then!
Come on, you failed scum...
We cannot
just sit here.
...and fight!
Jean, we were ordered by
Pierre to hold this bridge.
Orders be damned.
For the king.
For the king!
Thank you.
I will make no apology
for how you men fought today.
It was an honor
to be there with you.
Limoges is lost.
And our allies have failed
to take the port at Brest.
Our new Lord, Pierre,
has now resigned the campaign
and orders us home.
We move at dawn.
Hear, hear.
To the king.
Evidently,
Pierre is not happy.
Lives were saved.
Not in Limoges.
Let us return home,
my friend.
You saved
my life today.
Thank you.
Declare yourself!
Squire Jean de Carrouges.
Son of the captain
of this fort.
Open the gates!
It's a great honor
for Pierre
to have chosen your father's
castle for this ceremony.
I shall be prepared
to assume this captaincy
upon my father's passing.
Pray it is not
for many years.
Father. Mother.
Captain. Milady.
Squires.
Do not keep Our
Lord Pierre waiting.
...become your man.
I shall serve you for life.
So, Lord, I become your man.
I swear I shall serve you for life.
Milord, I become your man.
I shall serve you for life.
I swear I shall serve you for life.
Lord, I become your man.
- Lord...
- Closer.
Lord,
I become your man.
I swear I shall
serve you for life.
Declare yourself.
It is I.
Helen of Troy.
Le Gris.
It's good to see
you, my friend.
Though I do not come
only as a friend.
I'm afraid there's more to
my visit than I have let on.
Speak.
Pierre has charged me with
the collection of debts.
I see.
I have already visited all the
other tenants in his domain.
And now...
You have come
to see me.
I have come
to see you.
These levies are
for military defense.
And you know as well as
anyone our enemy's present.
And we need to be ready.
When have I not been ready to
stand and fight for my king?
You have.
More than any other.
But that's not all
this Pierre wants.
No, what Pierre wants...
Pierre wants the money
that he's rightfully owed.
I don't have it.
This plague has carried
off half my workforce.
My rent collection
is down.
My fields yield half
what they used to.
And the cost of labor
has now risen.
Yes.
How is it the other
vassals paid?
They paid because
I had to insist.
I see.
And now,
you insist upon me?
Let me talk to Pierre.
He's not without reason.
I will explain
your situation.
You are a true friend.
But I cannot return
empty-handed.
Of course not.
Thank you.
Let me see
what I have at hand.
- Think about this.
- I have.
You have not.
I will be fighting
under Admiral de Vienne.
The English are looting the
Cotentin Peninsula as we speak.
This plague has taken
your wife and son.
I will not stand by
whilst Lower Normandy falls.
Do not let
this obduracy take you.
You have no heir.
If you die, all you have
will revert to Count Pierre.
A fact not lost on
Pierre, I'm certain.
He does not favor me
as he does you.
No,
you have much to live for.
What do I have to live for, here?
What?
A name.
It's too great and storied a name
for you to treat it so recklessly.
Your father has
the captaincy of Belleme.
When he dies,
you will inherit that garrison
and everything that
comes with it.
And I am your friend.
And there are many others like me
who would prefer you not perish.
I don't embark on this
campaign recklessly.
I don't embark on it
just to fight.
Then why?
Jacques.
I am
broke.
I need money.
Long live the king!
They're back!
Quick! Come on! They're back!
I'll take
that from you.
Let me help you, sir.
Turn around,
please, my lord.
Lift, lift your arm.
Take them more bread.
Over here.
They want some more.
Robert de Thibouville.
He's providing shelter
and vittles for us.
De Thibouville?
Did he not side with the
English against us at Poitiers?
Yes, but he was pardoned
along with the others.
He's with us now.
And he'll stay that way if
he knows what's good for him.
Steady, Jean.
It's a roof
over our heads.
Besides,
he has quite
the wine cellar.
What a beauty.
She is
a de Thibouville?
Yes. Her name is
even older than yours.
She's his only daughter.
There's a dowry
to be had.
Of course, a man would
have to bear the mark
of her father's
disgrace...
I don't imagine one
would suffer too greatly
at the task of
producing an heir.
Gentlemen, welcome.
You fought bravely.
Thank you for hosting us.
- I would like to introduce...
- Jean de Carrouges.
Your reputation
precedes you.
As does yours.
It's my pleasure to
host you and your men.
It is only just to support the
men who fight for the king.
Some lessons are learned
later in life, hmm?
Allow me to introduce
my daughter.
Marguerite.
Marguerite, this is
Squire Jean de Carrouges.
Milady, I'm pleased
to meet you.
Pleasure is mine.
The dowry
includes this parcel as well.
Starting at
the hunting grounds.
What of this here?
The one to the north?
Aunou-le-Faucon.
As I say, starting at
the hunting grounds.
I'll have
that piece of land as well.
Most certainly.
Amen.
I'm a very
jealous man, milady.
Tonight, you are mine and
will dance with no other.
And every night
hereafter.
No need to worry.
This is it.
Property starts
at the river mouth
and extends all the way
to the hill beyond.
So, this is
Aunou-le-Faucon.
This was meant to be
part of Marguerite's dowry.
She loved it here.
And Pierre simply
gave it to you.
In appreciation
of my service.
His accounts were
in complete chaos.
Once I was able to reorder
them and collect the rents due,
everything started functioning
properly, and his fortunes turned.
Gave me this as a
sign of his gratitude.
It's not my doing.
The count is generous
and impetuous.
Let us eat.
I wish you'd seen
the gardens at Aunou-le-Faucon.
We had roses and lavender.
Then, we shall
have those here.
I remember my father built a swing
on the largest tree in the estate.
I will find the largest
tree and do the same.
I have such wonderful
memories of my summers there.
It's a pity Pierre
took that estate from your father.
I know you miss it.
It's the only way he
could pay what he owed.
Pierre then just gave it
to Jacques Le Gris as a gift.
Do all squires enjoy
such lavish gifts?
Le Gris more
than most.
He has become
Pierre's most trusted.
Perhaps Aunou-le-Faucon
is not gone for good.
Perhaps I shall not
let that rest.
Jean.
My love, I have
bled for this king.
He knows of me.
I may have more power
than you think.
I know how powerful
you are.
This land was promised to me
as part of my wife's dowry.
The petition
is denied.
This decision comes directly
from His Majesty, the king.
Are you
Squire Jean de Carrouges?
That is I.
What does it say?
'Tis your father.
Open the gate!
Leave us.
I was in Paris
when the news came.
Your father died quietly.
In his sleep.
I am lost.
They tell me I'm to leave
here within a month.
You will do
no such thing.
I will assume
the captaincy.
You will keep your
quarters, your servants.
Everything will be
the way it was...
Jean, have you
not heard?
You're not going to follow
in your father's footsteps
as captain here
at Belleme.
What do you mean?
Why did you have to sue the
count for a piece of land?
Just to impress
your bride.
That land was promised to me.
It was an appeal.
And now, you've made an
enemy of Count Pierre.
It was right.
Right.
There's no right.
There is only
the power of men.
You sued him,
and you've made a powerful enemy.
Your father was
a hard man
but there was much about this
world that he understood.
Who then will assume
my father's captaincy?
Good day!
Join us, my squire.
This is a day
for celebration.
I will not be
staying, milord.
I do not wish to interrupt
such an occasion,
but my honor
compels me to speak.
I was angered,
but I spoke well.
I said to Pierre,
"Can you stand there,
as a man of honor, as my liege lord,
"and say that I am not man enough
to assume my rightful captaincy
"that my grandfather and my father
held for the last 20 years of his life
"and take command
of that garrison
"and hold the fort of
Belleme for my king?"
And what said Pierre?
And there was Le Gris,
whose life I saved,
sitting by his side
with his captaincy,
not even man enough to look at me.
He poisons milord
with evil advice.
Whispered in his ear,
blackening my name.
Surely, you did not
say this.
You did.
We are no longer welcome
at court.
Jean...
So be it.
Milord.
Jean, an invitation
has arrived.
Your friend Jean Crespin
has invited us to his home.
They are celebrating the
birth of their first child.
It's a boy.
Oh, wonderful news.
It's been a year
since Belleme.
Perhaps we may
show our faces
so they know we carry on
in spite of this injustice.
A healthy child
in these times
is cause for
a celebration.
Do you think I would deny
the rabble of Argentan
the sight of
a true noblewoman?
Have a gown made.
This one is ready.
We need more hay over here.
I am very glad
you chose to attend.
This will only do you
good, my love.
Jean, I'm very pleased to see you.
It's been a long time.
Congratulations, my friend.
- Milady, you look lovely.
- Thank you.
Please, you're
most welcome.
Pardon me, milady.
- Le Gris.
- Carrouges.
Pax! Well done!
Well done, all!
Let there be no ill will among
the servants of the king.
He needs us all
right now.
Hear, hear.
Well spoken, old friend.
Marguerite, come.
Give our old friend
a kiss
and show the good faith
of the house Carrouges.
I will return in just a few
months, my love.
I will be safe and well attended
to by Alice and your mother,
but I will miss you.
This is what I do.
Let me provide for you.
And what of you?
I have all
that I need.
Except an heir.
My love.
It comes
as God wills it.
Be thou a knight
in the name of God.
Rise.
Jean de Carrouges!
In honor of your service
to our king.
Quiet!
Be thou a knight
in the name of God.
Rise.
All right, men!
Make preparations for battle!
Sire?
Why do they run?
For the king!
Our lord returns!
They're coming!
He's coming!
Welcome back, sire!
Milord,
you are not well.
This fever is all I've brought back
from that wretched place.
As well as
your knighthood.
Tomorrow,
I must go to Paris.
I'll be away one week.
What do you want?
I'm owed money
by the treasurer.
Jean, you are unwell.
He's well enough
to travel.
To Paris?
That's three days' ride.
And Argentan.
Duty demands that
I report to Pierre.
They will admire you
as a knight.
And you will confound
those who had not expected
you to return, Sir Jean.
Sir Jean de Carrouges?
Signature here.
300 gold pieces.
Sire.
I will be
in my chamber.
Good night.
My love?
What is the matter?
Has my mother quarreled
with you yet again?
No.
I have missed you.
Did you not miss me?
I missed you
more than you know.
Then let us go to bed.
- What? What is it, my love?
- I...
Uh...
Uh, When...
When you were gone, there was a day
when your mother had
business in Saint Pierre.
Yes.
She took the servants with her on
her errand, and I was left alone.
Did she not
leave Alice?
I told her in
no uncertain terms.
She took
all the servants.
Shortly after,
a man came unannounced.
I knew the man,
so I let him in.
But he was not alone.
He attacked me.
He pinned me down,
I protested.
I screamed, I cried out as best I
could, but there was no one here.
I was overpowered.
There was nothing I could do.
I was raped.
Who? Who did this?
Who?
Jacques Le Gris.
Are you telling me
the truth?
Yes. Yes.
Are you telling me
the truth?
Yes, I am telling you
the truth.
You must believe me.
You must.
You are my beloved.
Here.
I was not here
to protect you.
Please forgive me.
Please.
Jean.
I want him to answer
for what he has done.
And he will.
He will.
Collect the swords!
Show them in, please.
Take the horses down.
Move them aside.
Show them in, please.
And so,
I ask for your help.
Marguerite is my wife,
and she has been wronged.
I will not allow this
to go unpunished.
Your only avenue
is through Pierre.
Though I doubt he will
give you a hearing.
Tell the story
you've heard today.
Tell it anywhere you can
and to all who will listen.
We will be the subject
of gossip.
If the story is known
across Normandy,
Pierre will have to
grant us a hearing.
I have a plan.
I request a duel to the death.
This custom was outlawed
years ago.
Not so, Your Grace.
It is true that no duels have
been fought during your lifetime,
though it remains
acceptable as a venue...
It would require
a full convening
of the assembled
parliamentary body of Paris.
All 32 members of
Your Majesty's court.
One of us has lied.
Let us let God decide.
Sir Jean, if you
lose this duel,
thus proving these
accusations false,
your wife would suffer
dire consequences.
God will spare those
who tell the truth.
And the truth
will prevail.
I am not afraid.
Excellent.
His Majesty,
King Charles VI!
What is your
business today before this court?
Most excellent
and powerful king
and our sovereign lord,
I present myself,
Jean de Carrouges,
knight,
as an appellant
in your court
and hereby do
accuse this squire
of a most foul crime
against my wife,
the Lady Marguerite de
Carrouges.
I charge that during the third
week of this January past,
this same Jacques Le Gris
did feloniously
and carnally
take my wife against
her will in our house.
And if this said
Jacques Le Gris
denies his crime,
I stand ready
to prove my charge by
my body against his
and to render him dead
at an appointed time.
Come for your fight!
You're all gonna die!
You're all gonna
die like pigs!
Come on, then!
Come on,
you failed scum...
We cannot just sit here.
...and fight!
Jean, we were ordered by
Pierre to hold this bridge.
Orders be damned.
They're baiting
you, Jean.
They want us to leave the
bridge so they can take Limoges.
Then they shall
have their wish!
My son is a fool.
Let him go!
If he goes alone,
he will die.
For the king!
I know he is stubborn.
Yes, stubborn,
difficult, jealous,
- rash, dimwitted, irascible, dimwitted...
- Yes. Yes, yes, I know, milord.
...stupid. He does not exactly
yield his rents on time.
But I count him
as a friend.
He disobeyed me
and let Limoges fall.
He believed he would succeed.
His intentions were good.
He's no fucking fun.
You mean, you'd like to see more
of his gloom here in Argentan?
He postures and mopes about
like a black cloud.
Milord, I have fought with him and
seen the worst of this world with him.
He is loyal.
Yeah. So are my
fucking hounds.
As you wish. Take your leave.
Do as you like.
I think very little
of his character.
However, I think
a great deal of yours.
It's the quality that most
recommends you.
But do not let your loyalty
blind you.
- Thank you, milord.
- Yes.
Le Gris?
The gold? Or the sandal?
- Gold.
- Indeed.
The gold.
No, no.
I know, I know...
Ladies and gentlemen.
Under ordinary circumstances,
your hostess, the viscountess,
my wife,
Lady Marie Chamaillart,
would see the sun come
up with all of us,
sing louder,
dance more
and drink you all
under the table.
However, she's fast at work
growing our eighth child
in 14 years of marriage.
Well, good night,
dear friends.
I shall wait up for
absolutely none of you.
Especially my husband.
Good night, dear.
My love.
- Hear, hear.
Good night.
Well, now,
perhaps the evening can truly begin.
Where were we?
Uh... Latour, read.
I do not read Latin.
You do not even read.
I will read.
The Book of Love.
- Ooh.
- Rule number 24.
Anyone?
Squire?
"A new love
expels an old one."
Too true.
Well, it appears we have a
squire with a hidden talent.
Read, do read.
Uh...
The rule
of love number four.
"Love is always growing,
"or diminishing."
Insolent bastard!
He knows you.
"Nothing prevents a
woman from being loved by two men.
"Or a man from being
loved by two women."
Well read.
Oh. Come, come.
If you run,
I will only chase you.
Wow, he grows serious.
No! No! No!
No!
This customer is rough.
And strong.
Here, come take
some evil inside you.
- Pierre!
- Oh.
Come, Pierre.
Great!
Pierre.
Life is good.
The wolves
have not slept, either.
Your wife will
awaken soon, milord.
Best be in there
when she does.
Pregnant and hysterical.
I prefer to take my chances
with the wolves.
So, tell me, squire,
how does a man of war
become so learned in letters?
I was born with neither
a name nor wealth.
I prepared for
a life in the church.
The requirements
did not suit me.
No, no.
A libertine after
my own heart.
That always
came to me easily.
Does that knowledge
also apply to numbers?
It does, milord.
Then let me share this with
you, and this stays between us.
Of course.
My accounts are in disarray.
Would you mind bringing your
expertise to bear on my finances?
How can this be?
Rents are late to come in.
The accountants are careless.
Milord, these nobles are holding the money
that they are meant to yield up to you.
The plague has carried off
half our workforce.
Crop yields are down.
Labor costs are up.
I understand the numbers,
and absolutely none of
this is your concern.
You need to be prepared to raise
an army at a moment's notice.
None of this works
if you're not solvent.
And when they say
they do not have it?
Well, let them
say that to me.
Well, then.
I was trying to have a word
with your lord.
This matter is between us.
Do not interrupt me again.
All right,
let us look at the map.
Shall we?
There is, of course,
my property here at Bourg.
No.
My good man, no.
What's this here?
Aunou-le-Faucon.
No.
It's one of my most
valuable estates.
It is to be part of
my daughter's dowry.
I cannot just
give it to him.
My friend, Pierre's not asking you
to give him your finest estate.
But Aunou-le-Faucon
is worth twice what I owe.
Well, think of how good it will
feel to be completely without debt.
Have you heard?
Reports from the north.
They say there's a father
so desperate,
he'll marry his own daughter
to Jean de Carrouges.
Indeed?
Yes, Robert de Thibouville,
the traitor.
Carrouges needs an heir.
Is she the only
noblewoman in Normandy?
He needs money as well.
There's much
to recommend her.
She's rich, young.
They say she's beautiful.
Yes, and her father
betrayed the Crown.
I make no apologies
for Robert de Thibouville.
Yeah. Only a shame he wasn't
beheaded for his treason.
He would have been spared
the sight of this humiliation.
Gently.
Yeah. Here, boy.
Stag's blood.
Badge of honor.
Well done, Etienne!
Uh, Charles.
What?
He's suing me.
Oh. Come in.
Take your pants off.
He's suing me!
- Who?
- Me!
For land that is
rightfully mine.
Jean de Carrouges has filed a
lawsuit for a piece of property.
Why would he sue you
for a piece of property?
Because you gave it
to me.
He's suing you, too.
He's suing us both.
I fail to see the amusement
here, milord.
How do you sue for that
which was never yours?
My squire.
Will you finally submit that I
was right about Jean de Carrouges?
He's saying he will take
the matter to the king.
He has bled
for this king.
My cousin, the king.
Pierre.
So have I bled.
So have you.
My friend,
this matter is settled.
I'd hoped to
surprise you at court.
Now, you have barged in and cast a
pall over a rather promising evening.
So, I will tell you now.
Jean de Carrouges will not be
the new captain at Belleme.
You will be the new
captain at Belleme.
As if by magic.
Carrouges will
be furious.
Too true.
Now take your fucking pants off.
Minor delay.
Who wants to help me
restore my previous state?
Come here.
Come down, my boy!
Le Gris!
I will protect this
fortress of Belleme
and command its garrison
as captain
to the best of my ability
against any and all
enemies of my king.
Jacques Le Gris.
Captain, rise
and be recognized.
Good day!
Join us, my squire.
This is a day
for celebration.
I will not be
staying, milord.
Good God, man, tell me you're
not here to sue me again.
Mock me, if you may,
but you cannot change right
from wrong nor wrong from right.
Enlighten me, my squire,
as to what is right.
For as I see it, last time you
emerged was to file suit against me
for land I lawfully owned
and gifted to my most
faithful of squires
for services rendered
by him unto me.
What claim could you possibly
have had to this land?
You have owned it never.
I know all
about your squire.
The squire you
gifted the land to.
The one who holds a captaincy
now that is rightfully mine.
My friend, please.
- Come, let us talk in private.
- No! No! No!
I shall be heard!
I do not accept this!
My father, for 20 years,
my father...
I've waited for 20 years!
There's not a nobleman in this hall
who would speak ill of your father.
You ask for my rents,
I yield them up.
Here, as a man of honor,
you say I am not the captain?
You say to me
I am not the captain here?
I say to you
whatever I like.
I decide who is the captain
at Belleme.
That is what you prize.
That. That sycophant.
Sycophants all!
I will sue!
I will sue you for this!
In just three years,
you've managed to marry
a traitor's daughter,
sue me for land that never
belonged to you
and to stand before me for the
second time in as many years,
threatening
once again to sue,
all while speaking
of duty and honor.
This is how you serve me?
I serve the king.
The king.
Heaven and earth!
Heaven and earth what?
14.
37. 45.
15. 17 borrowed...
Come.
Hello.
Thought you were
asleep, milord.
Aye, great,
good friend.
No, almost,
but I spied candlelight,
and I knew it must be you.
I work better alone.
You make it hard for a man
to get his work done.
I came here to tell you
I will not be joining you
for Crespin's celebration.
Milord?
Too far a ride,
too cold.
We'll stay here and
fuck women of our own.
- No.
No, I'm told Jean de
Carrouges will be there.
It's time to
heal this wound.
He will never change.
Why even try?
Because a feud between
your lordship's vassals
brings naught but trouble
and distraction.
Oh, good God.
And because I once stood
godfather to his late son!
I once held a place
in his heart.
Do as you must.
You will get to see
the mysterious wife.
Apparently, he's letting her out
of the dungeon for one time only.
One can only hope he hasn't
taken away her books.
Carrouges' wife reads?
In as many languages
as you do, I'm told.
Strange match.
It is. Will wonders never cease?
- Come to the celebration, milord!
- No.
- Come!
Too much wine.
My Latin fails me.
"We forgive a child
afraid of the dark.
"Tragedy is men
afraid of the light."
Your decency will be
the end of you.
And there is no end
to my decency.
No, milord!
Recalculate!
Sorry.
I think you'd enjoy it.
We will ride from the valley
to where the river ends.
We could, uh, dine there.
My servants could prepare
a picnic.
Oh, Jacques Le Gris,
save your breath.
I've heard all about you
from the ladies at court.
They're...
They're just boasting.
Carrouges.
Pardon me, milady.
Le Gris.
Pax! Well done!
Well done, all!
Let there be no ill will among
the servants of our king.
His Majesty needs
us all right now.
Hear, hear. Well spoken.
Marguerite, come.
Give my old friend
a kiss.
Show him the good faith
of the house Carrouges.
Bravo!
If we...
There.
I think...
There you go.
It's a shame we had
not met until tonight.
Is it?
I had no idea what a
lucky man Carrouges was
for having such
a beautiful wife.
From what I have heard,
you have no trouble
acquiring beautiful women.
And from
what I have heard,
we may have a great
deal in common.
What could we possibly
have in common?
Appreciation of one another's
extraordinary good looks.
You are quite talented
when it comes to flattery.
I only
speak the truth.
And what else?
You are a reader?
Like myself.
Romance of the Rose.
I thought it rather dull.
Dull?
The book is wretched.
I much prefer
Percival's Courtesy.
It's a much more challenging
and interesting novel.
Smart woman.
Tell me.
He is naïve & foolish.
Yet he is of so pure a
heart he's able to claim the Grail.
I admire that.
I understand him.
He knows what he desires...
...and doesn't give up
until he attains it.
Good minds belong together.
Don't
get ahead of yourself.
Carrouges.
Your wife charms me,
my friend.
To even think is to covet,
my lord.
No less sinful
than her coveting me.
Please forgive me.
I wish...
Milord?
I've never seen you
like this, milord.
Nor have I, my friend.
Word is not promising
on the Scottish front.
Perhaps the Lady Marguerite's
already a widow.
I would not wager against
Jean de Carrouges in battle.
What do you think
her and Jean speak about?
You think
they read together?
But he's illiterate,
though, isn't he?
The debt we owe to our friends
is the greatest of all.
Is it greater than love?
I didn't train him properly.
The fault is mine.
My lords! My lords!
I present the knight,
Sir Jean de Carrouges!
Milord, I return from the royal
campaign in Scotland to report to you.
Rise, Sir Knight, speak.
We found ourselves unwelcome
by our Scottish allies.
We laid siege at Wark.
Louder, Sir Knight,
they cannot hear you in the back.
We laid siege at Wark.
Mm.
Milord, I return
with neither plunder
nor prisoners.
And without five of the nine
squires under my command.
Indeed,
I return a knight.
One who curses Scotland and
the hour I set foot there.
Yes.
Word had arrived
ahead of you
of your
calamitous campaign.
A tragic result, Jean,
though, I dare say,
no fault of your command.
Hear, hear!
Where are you off to now, Jean?
I'm bound for Paris.
I have business with the
treasurer for my payment.
Very good.
A good soldier and good
fortune are not long parted.
I return a knight.
That is the second time
you do not call me "sir."
There will not be a third.
No offense intended,
Sir Jean.
I will not be patronized
by this squire
who lies about court,
waiting to be feted
with gift
upon gift upon gift
and risks nothing!
Nothing.
He may acquire more
property in this world,
find more favor...
...eat more, drink more,
bed more,
and otherwise,
call himself a man of arms.
But in this hall
and any other,
in my company,
he will call me "sir."
Sir.
Indeed,
good sir.
Enjoy your time in Paris,
Sir Jean.
That is all, Jean.
Milord.
Who's there?
It's, uh, I, Adam Louvel,
milady.
Adam Louvel?
I'm ashamed to have
to ask a great favor.
My horse has thrown
a shoe and...
Nobody's here.
I'm not permitted
to open the door.
No, of course.
I just wondered if I could come inside
and warm myself while he's reshod.
I'm so sorry to have to ask.
For a moment. I hate to ask.
- Oh...
- I...
Milady,
forgive me for intruding.
I love you more than any other,
and I would do anything for you.
Everything I have is yours.
How can you speak to me
like this?
Marguerite, what way then
would I speak to you?
Milady, you must know
it cannot be helped.
My love for you
has consumed me.
How dare you?
Milady, when milord sets
his course for love...
- Do not speak!
- You must leave now. Please.
You heard the lady.
Leave us!
Milord.
- I am married.
- Yes.
You are saddled with
a terrible burden.
A cold, callous man who
does not love you as I do.
Who cannot appreciate you
for the marvel that you are.
- Please.
- I only want for your happiness.
I cannot bear to see
you in such hardship.
I know your house's
finances are fragile.
My lord provides for me.
Yes.
But does he know
you to be the most...
exquisite...
fascinating woman?
A woman
I would devote
my whole life to.
Oh, hear me say
I'm in love with you.
I know you love me, too.
You must.
You must leave.
Now, please.
Jeanette!
If you run,
I will only chase you.
- No.
- Yes.
No.
No!
Please, no.
You fear yourself guilty,
but, my love,
I beseech you,
tell no one.
For your own safety.
If your husband
hears of this,
he may kill you.
Say nothing.
I will keep quiet, too.
Do not feel badly,
my love.
We could not
help ourselves.
Forgive me, Father,
for I have sinned.
Speak, my son.
I carry a sin that weighs
heavy upon my heart.
What is it, my son?
I have committed
the sin of adultery
against a man I once
considered a friend.
You know
your commandments?
Yes, Father.
I ask forgiveness.
My son,
Matthew tells us,
everyone who looks
at a woman with lust
has already committed adultery
with her in his heart.
But is love a sin, Father?
How can I seek absolution
for love?
This is the work
of the Devil.
This temptress
leads you astray.
Just as Eve lured Adam
from the divine path.
That is not love.
Then why?
God is faithful.
He will not let you be tempted
beyond what you can bear.
This is a test.
- My friend.
- Milord.
Sit.
You will need to sit.
Drink this.
You should drink
all of it.
There is no other way
to say this
than to speak plainly.
A most unspeakable charge
has been brought against you.
Jean de Carrouges
evidently,
among others,
has been telling any
and all who will listen
that you...
took his wife
against her will.
I know not what to say.
Why would she say that?
Jacques, it is
you and I here.
I must know.
This is a serious matter.
The accusation is false.
Of course, she made the customary
protest, but she is a lady.
It was not
against her will.
Why would I ever
need to do that?
Have you ever known me to
lack the company of women?
No.
But you have not
been yourself of late.
It is true, I confess,
it is a feeling I've never had before.
A love...
that I've never known.
It...
It's taken all my strength
not to return to her.
We knew it was wrong,
I confessed my adultery,
and performed my penance.
But I swear to you,
this charge of rape is false.
Of course it's absurd.
It's as I suspected.
But I must
defend my name.
No, you must
do no such thing.
On my honor, I will, milord.
I must.
I know you yearn to defend
your name and your honor,
but the common mind has no
capacity for this sort of nuance.
They simply don't understand
the world as we do.
They see villains and
heroes, that is all.
Milord...
Deny, deny, deny.
Everywhere, always,
at all times, and to all men.
You did not
commit adultery.
It never happened.
There is no proof.
It will always be your word
against that of Jean de Carrouges.
Yes, milord.
Of course we will have
to endure a public trial,
charges of rape will
be brought against you
and a verdict will be
rendered by your overlord
adjudicating this
matter who,
as the fates
would have it,
happens to be me.
I hereby find said Jacques Le
Gris to be completely innocent
and wholly without guilt.
I order the criminal
complaint annulled
and stricken
from the record.
Let there be no further
questions about it.
Let there be
no more gossip,
the penalty a
punishment by my hand.
Is that understood?
As to the sworn testimony
of Lady Marguerite,
one can only come to the
conclusion she must have dreamt it.
Now, have these findings
sent immediately to Paris
before this insouciant knight troubles
our king any further with this nonsense.
Yes, speak.
Milord, I have
been informed
that Jean de Carrouges has
already travelled to Paris.
He is filing an appeal to His
Majesty at this very moment.
Cunt.
The benefit of clergy.
There really is
no decision to make.
You're a cleric
in minor orders.
So, you can escape the
jurisdiction of the secular courts
and be tried
by the Church
where conditions are
more favorable.
Men holding church office
number disproportionately
among those accused of rape.
They escape serious punishment by
claiming benefit of clergy, so...
we'll have the church try your
case and be done with the matter.
But what of my name?
Was there
an affair?
Absolutely not.
It's strange she would claim
rape and risk her life.
Why would she do this?
All of France is talking about
this, and I'm innocent.
I've said publicly
that this never happened!
And yet,
under extraordinary pressure
and at great risk
to her name and reputation,
Lady Marguerite has
said that it did.
Formally, this is
not about her.
Rape is not a crime
against a woman.
It is a property crime
against her male guardian.
In this case,
Jean de Carrouges.
This is not a matter over which a
duel should be fought to the death.
It should be
settled quietly.
Take the benefit of clergy.
I'm not a coward.
Most excellent and powerful
king and our sovereign lord,
I present myself,
Jacques Le Gris,
squire and defendant,
and I do hereby deny
all the aforesaid charges,
especially
of Jean de Carrouges,
that I did unlawfully...
and carnally
know his wife,
the Lady Marguerite de
Carrouges,
in the third week
of January last,
or at any other time.
And I further maintain,
saving the honor of Your Majesty,
that the said knight
has falsely
and wickedly lied!
And that he is false
and wicked
to say this thing.
And I further maintain...
and with the aid of God,
and with Our Lady,
I pledge to do whatever is
necessary to prove my innocence.
The knight and the squire
have spoken well.
It is ordered now that the
parties present the affidavits
which, the court
having received,
will render a verdict
upon in a fortnight.
If either man
attempts to flee Paris,
it will be taken as
a sign of his guilt.
Orders will be issued
for his summary arrest
and he will be hanged.
The king will decide if a duel
should indeed be fought.
What now?
You will
have 330 livres in coin,
furnishings, cloth, and jewels
in addition to the estate
at Mont a Gudot as well as...
And what of
Aunou-le-Faucon?
Uh, I was forced to sell that
property to Count Pierre.
You and I agreed
this land should be assumed
by whomever marries
your daughter.
Is this not part
of the dowry?
I was unable
to pay my rents.
You promised me.
We discussed this.
My daughter comes with the
money and the land that I've offered.
That is all that I own.
And what
of the bride price?
I offer you
a name of value.
I should expect she's capable
of performing her wifely duties?
Bearing an heir.
My daughter
is strong and healthy
and ready to honor
the marriage.
The conception of an heir and
children to follow shall be swift.
And prolific.
Proceed.
The
wedding will proceed!
You're perfect.
I hope this was
pleasurable for you.
Yes, milord, very.
I could not have asked
for a more
satisfying wedding night.
Perhaps we have conceived
on this very night.
I think you would enjoy it.
We will ride
- from the valley to where the river...
- Milord. Carrouges.
Carrouges.
Le Gris.
Pax! Well done!
Well done, all!
Let there be no ill will
between servants of our king.
Marguerite, come.
Give my old friend a kiss.
Show him the good faith
of the house Carrouges.
Who is that squire?
He's dangerously handsome.
Mm. He has quite
the reputation.
Should milord not
return from battle,
I would happily strengthen
that reputation.
Mm, I think that could
be arranged regardless.
- Marie.
- How can you speak like this?
I should not be seen
nor heard with you.
My husband would
have my head.
But you would die happy.
He's handsome.
Charming, I hear.
True, he is handsome
and charming,
but my husband
does not trust him.
I am proud of you.
I know that this reconciliation
must have been difficult.
You gave me good counsel.
You are kind
to Jacques Le Gris.
That man is unduly
fond of himself.
But you see
how a smile and a kind word
go much further than a threat.
Even if you don't mean it.
While I'm gone,
besides a bountiful harvest,
our fortunes will turn most on
the breeding of these horses.
And the collection
of rents?
Yes, of course.
Stand over there.
I bought this mare
for breeding.
Comes from a long line
of war horses.
She will foal many
a valuable colt.
Sometimes,
the difference
between victory
and defeat,
between life and death...
- Get out of the way!
Mind the gate!
No!
Whoa! Steady!
- Whoa, whoa, whoa!
- No!
Steady, girl.
- Easy! Easy!
- Get hold of her.
Not the stallion!
No! Not you!
Not with my mare!
The gates remain closed!
Yes, milord.
The mare is in season!
These are not
trifling matters.
It costs money.
Nothing would get done around
here were it not for me.
I trust your little death was a
memorable and a productive one.
It was like none other.
Why have I not yet conceived?
I want a child so very badly.
Wanting a child has nothing to
do with the matter, Marguerite.
We need a son.
You think
I do not know this?
I think of nothing else.
I did not have this problem
with my first wife.
I shall return
in a few months.
You will be safe here with
my mother and your servants.
You must never allow yourself
to be unattended.
And do not look so sad.
I prefer you to be in good
spirits as I go off to war.
I'm proud of you, milord.
You will take care
of the estate.
See that it does not
fall into disarray.
Of course.
- Good morning.
- Milady.
Good morning, Henri.
Good morning
to you, milady.
The pregnancy
seems to be going well.
Yes, milady.
So why is she penned up?
Before my master left,
he had told me to do so.
My husband knows much
about horses,
riding them.
The upbringing,
I leave to you.
It would be better
for the health of the mare
to be roaming free.
Then she shall roam free.
Thank you, milady.
This is last month's
rent as well, milady.
Were you unable to pay?
Your lord never came
to collect it.
- Is this unusual?
- No.
But it is no trouble.
Thank you.
Henri?
Yes, milady?
Are the oxen
not too slow?
The thaw came late
this year.
It's been hard
going for them.
If we are to sow the oats
in time for harvest,
then we must be
much faster.
I should like to
use the horses.
Yes, but we never use the
horses for that purpose.
My master feels
they are too valuable.
They will be of no value if they
starve to death this winter.
See that it's done.
Right away.
I see you have some sun
on your face, milady.
- You look well.
- Do I?
I prefer not to be pink.
Though it was
a lovely day.
A little color on one's
face proves they're alive.
Barely.
Have you heard we've a
famous tailor from Paris
arriving in the village
next week?
You've been working hard,
why not buy yourself a new dress?
Oh, I don't know.
He copies the dresses Queen
Isabeau's been seen wearing.
They're quite the rage.
I have seen those.
The neckline
is very low.
Almost so low that one might
see the queen's pierced nipples.
She does not.
- She does.
- She does not...
Good evening.
Things seem to be
running quite well.
I enjoy doing
these tasks.
It's my pleasure.
Until he returns
from Scotland,
of course.
It is unfortunate,
however,
that you've not
been capable
of steering your husband away
from conflict with others.
Jean does what he feels
is necessary.
May I ask what you're making?
It looks lovely.
I say with sorrow,
something
apparently fruitless.
You are very cruel.
I am a good wife.
As long as you are fulfilling
your wifely duties.
Or perhaps you cannot
be pleased.
How is your sleep?
Often interrupted.
Flaccid joints.
Bitter taste in the mouth?
I don't know.
My lady, it appears you are suffering
from an imbalance of the four humors,
primarily black bile.
You are severely
melancholic,
your body is
cold and dry.
Perhaps this,
combined with various
other factors,
including God's will,
could be
preventing conception.
It is imperative that you
have a pleasurable conclusion
similar to your husband's,
in order to conceive a child.
You achieve this?
Yes.
You find intercourse with
your husband pleasurable?
Yes, of course, Doctor.
Although I am not certain
I am experiencing
"the little death,"
as they say.
But if you find it
pleasurable, then you are.
Very well.
When Jean returns,
he shall be grateful
as I have put the books in order,
as well as everything else.
Perhaps he won't mind
the expense.
Let us both get dresses.
Surprise your new husband.
He would not approve.
He would say I have
enough dresses.
I've only been married
a short time,
yet I now understand the
burden of this arrangement.
You are a newlywed.
Surely you do not
feel burdened.
Bernard is a frugal man
and he does not like
to kiss me.
I once thought his appearance
would become more pleasing,
but, instead,
it's become more repulsive.
So I suppose I am relieved
about the kissing.
He is not like Jean,
handsome and generous.
My marriage is not
without its problems.
I shall be right with
you, ladies.
Thank you.
Despite Le Gris'
many deplorable qualities,
one cannot be blind
to his appearance.
Crude as he is.
Offensive as well.
- They're all such fools.
- Hmm.
Agreed.
Welcome back, sire.
Welcome home, my love.
I am so happy
to see you.
My God, Marguerite,
have you lost your dignity?
Go upstairs before the
others think you a harlot.
I am your wife.
Welcome home,
my courageous son.
Thank you.
Had I seen the gown
or known it was being made,
I would've stopped it.
And how would you have
done that in my household?
I wonder.
Are you gonna let your wife
speak to me in a tone like this?
Marguerite is a grown
woman, Mother.
The decisions she makes
are her own.
As well as
the lessons learned.
Tomorrow I must go to Paris.
I'll be away one week.
But you are ill.
You must stay here, indoors.
Yes, please stay.
I'm owed money.
- I intend to collect it.
- Of course.
Perhaps you may
visit some old friends.
Le Gris is in Argentan.
Why Le Gris?
Please ensure Alice is
with her while I'm away.
I forbid you from
leaving the grounds.
It's not safe.
I...
I should like to
see my friends.
We're so isolated.
Precisely.
Mm.
Whoa!
- Are you leaving?
- Yes.
Well, when will
you return?
When my tasks
are completed.
Before nightfall.
Jean insisted I not be left alone.
You heard him.
- Antoine!
- Hyah!
Sow!
Eight, nine,
ten, eleven, twelve...
Stay.
Who is there?
It is I.
Adam Louvel, milady.
Uh...
Adam Louvel?
- Hello.
- I, uh...
I have a great favor
to ask.
My horse has thrown a shoe.
Uh...
Nobody is here. I am not
permitted to open the door.
Of course.
I understand.
If I could...
Could I wait inside
while he's reshod?
Just to warm myself
for a moment.
- I...
- Will not be long at all.
Uh, it's just
an inconvenience.
- I'm so sorry to have to ask.
- Please.
Oh, I'm not alone.
Milady, forgive me
for intruding.
I love you.
More than any other.
And I would do
anything for you.
Everything I have
is yours.
How can you
speak to me this way?
Marguerite, what way then
would I speak to you?
Milady must know
it cannot be helped.
My love for you
has consumed me.
How dare you?
Milady, when milord sets
his course for love...
You must leave now. Please.
You heard the lady!
Leave us.
Milord.
- I am married.
- Yes.
And you are saddled
with a terrible burden.
A cold, callous man who
does not love you as I do.
Who cannot appreciate you
for the marvel that you are.
Oh, please,
do not speak of my husband.
I want only
for your happiness.
I cannot bear to see
you in such hardship.
I know your house's
finances are fragile.
My lord provides for me.
Yes.
But does he know you
to be the most exquisite,
fascinating woman?
A woman I would devote
my whole life to.
Ah, hear me say
I'm in love with you.
And I know
you love me too.
You must.
You must leave.
Please.
Marguerite,
do not fight this.
Jeanette!
If you run,
I will only chase you.
Jeanette!
No! No!
Come here.
No.
No!
No! No! No!
No! Please.
- Shh.
- Please, don't do this.
Please.
This is our moment.
Oh,
you feel yourself guilty.
Oh, but, my love,
I beseech you, tell no one.
For your own safety.
If your husband hears of this,
he may kill you.
Say nothing.
Do not feel badly,
my love.
We could not
help ourselves.
Milady, we've returned.
She was trying a new cook,
and the dish was quite tasty,
save for the cheese.
I've never enjoyed this particular
cheese, but sadly, it's everywhere.
Thank you.
There is one example,
and I've forgotten
the name of it, um...
it has various colors laced through it.
Oh, uh...
Do you know
the name of this cheese?
I think that
it is Roquefort.
No. No, no, not Roquefort.
It's not as strong as Roquefort.
But it has a certain texture
that is very good in cookery.
Milady.
You haven't been eating.
Are you ill?
Lady Carrouges has enquired
about your state of mind.
Uh, my state of mind is fine.
Thank you, Alice.
Do not open the door.
It's Marie. I'm here to see Marguerite.
Is she in?
Fine.
It's me.
- Come on in.
- Good day.
Marguerite!
I've never felt such joy.
I'm pregnant.
Are you...
Are you all right?
You don't seem yourself.
Are you not happy for me?
I'm so very pleased for you.
Sire.
I have missed you.
Did you not miss me?
Oh, I missed you
more than you know.
- Then let us go to bed.
- Jean...
- Marguerite, I've been away for many days.
- I cannot.
What do you mean,
you cannot?
Well, um,
I need to tell you something.
What?
While you were gone, there was a
day when your mother had business
in Saint Pierre.
Yes.
And shortly after,
a man came, unannounced.
I knew the man,
so I let him in.
But he was not alone.
Jacques Le Gris entered our home
without my permission and...
- What about Le Gris?
- He forced me to this room.
To this bed.
He raped me.
Are you telling me
the truth?
Please.
Are you
telling me the truth?
Jean, please! I am telling you the truth.
You must believe me.
I screamed.
I screamed until
I lost my voice.
He forced you?
He raped me.
- You did not provoke this?
- No, Jean.
Could you not run?
I was pinned down,
I could not breathe.
Can this
man do nothing but evil to me?
Jean, I intend
to speak the truth.
I will not be silent.
I have no legal standing
without your support.
Then you shall
have it.
Come.
I will not allow him to be the
last man to have known you.
- Jean...
- Come.
Come!
Milady,
do you swear upon your life
that what you say is true?
I swear it.
Will you swear it
before God?
And all of France?
I will.
Then we fight.
Marguerite is my wife
and we have been wronged.
I will not allow it
to go unpunished.
Your only avenue
is through Pierre.
Though I doubt he will
give you a hearing.
Tell the story
you heard today.
Tell it anywhere you can
and to all who will listen.
We will be the subject
of gossip.
If the story is known
across Normandy,
Pierre will have to
grant us a hearing.
We have a plan.
Marie?
Stay a while.
Why can't you look at me?
I cannot.
Marie?
Do you not recall?
You said, on one or more occasions,
that you found Le Gris handsome.
So did you.
But I do not
complain of rape.
Marie!
You do not believe me.
I have to go.
No, Jean, no!
This is not what I want!
Not what you want?
Can he not simply be tried for
his crime in the courts?
Pierre is the courts!
If you appeal to the king,
he will only side with Pierre
as he has in the past.
I will not appeal
to the king.
I will appeal to God.
Marguerite,
why have you done this?
Because what happened
to me is wrong.
Men like Le Gris take
women when they want
and how often they want.
Who do you think you are?
My son may die.
That is his choice.
Not mine.
You are no different from the peasants
our soldiers have their way with
when they are at war.
Do they complain?
I cannot be silent.
I must speak.
Marguerite!
All you have done is
bring shame to our family.
I am telling the truth.
The truth
does not matter.
You look at me as if
I were never young.
I was raped.
And despite my protestations
and my revulsion,
did I go crying to my lord
who had better things
to worry about?
No, I stood up,
got on with my life.
But at what cost?
At what cost?
I'm alive.
Well, you have paid a dear
price for that privilege.
I have heard from several
sources that you told others
you found
Monsieur Le Gris handsome.
Perhaps you dreamt
this event,
wishing it to be true.
Yes, a long time ago,
some friends and I agreed
that he was handsome, but I told them
that I knew him to be untrustworthy.
Noticing a man is attractive
reveals nothing but that.
And if one of these
women is your dearest friend,
why would she bring this
information to the court?
I do not know.
You've been with Jean
de Carrouges for how many years?
Five.
In that time,
you've not carried a child,
an heir to the family name.
No, monsieur. No.
And yet,
here you are,
six months from the incident
you claim is true,
and you are
six months pregnant.
Perhaps you have
another lover
and accuse Le Gris
to hide this.
As I have said,
I am loyal to my husband.
Do you enjoy having
intercourse with your husband?
Yes, of course.
It is not
a matter of course.
You are fully aware that
you cannot conceive a child
unless you
experience pleasure
- at the end.
- Yes.
Yes.
And do you experience
pleasure at the end?
Yes. I do.
A rape cannot
cause a pregnancy.
This is just science.
It permits
the court to wonder
if after five years
of marital relations,
your pregnancy is
a coincidence.
Let us say we believe
you are telling the truth
and such an act did,
in fact, take place,
perhaps you enjoyed it
more than you're
willing to admit.
Please, explain to me
how one is to enjoy rape.
Did you
experience pleasure?
Simply answer
the question.
I experienced no pleasure!
Are there
any more questions?
If your husband were to lose the duel,
it would demonstrate God's judgment
and reveal you for having
borne false witness.
I understand.
I'm certain
your husband told you,
the penalty for bearing false
witness against a man by a woman,
in the case of rape,
is that you are to be
stripped and shorn,
fitted by the neck
with an iron collar,
lashed to a wooden post,
and summarily burned alive.
Lady Marguerite...
it is quite common
for the accused to burn
for 20 to 30 minutes
before they are dead.
I am telling the truth.
We will proceed
with the duel.
You think Le Gris handsome,
do you?
You have disgraced me
before my king
and all of France.
You knew what would happen to
me should you lose this duel.
You knew and
you didn't tell me.
God will not punish
those who tell the truth.
My fate and our child's fate
will be written,
not by God's will,
but by which old man
will tire first.
How dare you
speak to me this way.
What have I to lose?
I begged you to find another way,
and now I may be burned alive.
- I am risking my life for you.
- Hmm.
You are risking my life
so you can fight your enemy
and save your pride.
And that could render
our child an orphan.
Or did you not
think of that?
You are a hypocrite.
You are blinded
by your vanity.
All the preparations
are made.
I'm ready.
I should like to stay
a while longer.
Faith, Marguerite.
I finally gave birth to a son who I love
more than I could have ever imagined...
and I may not live
to see him grow.
This was my life.
Had I had known the truth
would deprive me of this love,
I believe I would have done what
many women before me had done.
Nothing.
- What you did was right.
- Mm.
Not if I die.
I am not like you, Jean.
A child needs his mother
more than a mother
needs to be right.
Knights, proceed.
Lady,
upon your evidence,
I hazard my life in combat
with Jacques Le Gris.
You know my cause
is just and true.
I say before all of you,
I spoke the truth.
Let it be
in God's hands.
There'll be rough justice
this day by the grace of God.
Let us pray this ends
like the duel at Flanders.
With Le Gris in a wrestling match,
removing Carrouges' testicles by hand.
Let them go!
Let them go! Let them go!
Quickly! Give it to me!
Lance, lance! Hurry!
Whoa. Whoa!
Out of the way!
Lance! Lance!
Axe, axe!
Carrouges may yet
bleed out.
Pray God.
Kill him! Kill him!
- Kill him!
- Kill him! Kill him!
Confess!
Confess to me.
Carrouges, there was no rape.
There was no rape.
There was no rape!
In the name of God
and on the peril of
damnation of my soul,
I am innocent of the crime!
Then you be damned.
Yes.
God be with
you, milady.
No...
Rise. You rise.
I grace you
with honor, knight.
God has spoken,
proving your cause
to be truthful and just.
You have fought
with strength and humility.
May God be with you
and your wife.
Your wife.
Long live Carrouges!
Carrouges!
The glory of Carrouges!
Look at that!